Guide to the Kerby Miller Papers AIA.076
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Kerby Miller Papers
Bulk, 1760-2003
1660-2003
AIA.076
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
9.25 linear feet in 9 record cartons and 1 oversized flat box
Kerby A. Miller is a historian and Curators’ Professor at the University of Missouri. Miller graduated from Pomona College in 1966 and University of California, Berkley with an M.A. in 1967 and a Ph.D in 1976. His teaching and published work focuses on Irish history, often with an emphasis on social, immigration, and urban history. This collection consists of materials created or collected by Kerby Miller in the course of his research, teaching, and writing on Irish and Irish American history. Materials include photocopies of American Loyalists' petitions to the British government, a run of British Information Services news bulletins concerning conflict in Northern Ireland, and research materials created in the course of his academic scholarship, including original writings, reviews of his work, photocopied letters from Irish immigrants and citizens, and correspondence between Miller and other academics and institutions. Major subjects and themes present in these research files include pre- and post-immigration economic issues, experiences coming to and first impressions of living in America, genealogical records, and accounts of Irish family life.
Miller, Kerby A.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist, but groupings of materials have been identified based on similar content and context of creation. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Kerby Miller in April 2015. The accession number associated with this gift is 2015.018. An additional 8 boxes were donated in June of 2015 as accession 2015.051 and added as "Academic Research and Writing" series.
Related Archival Materials
Archives of Irish America Irish Republicanism Papers (AIA 022)
Frank Durkan Papers (AIA 008)
Bruce Boling Papers (AIA 062)
Paul O'Dwyer Papers (AIA 069)
Historical/Biographical Note
Kerby A. Miller is a historian and Curators’ Professor at the University of Missouri. Miller graduated from Pomona College in 1966 and University of California, Berkley with an M.A. in 1967 and a Ph.D in 1976. His teaching and published work often focus on Irish and Irish American history, with an emphasis on social, immigration, and urban issues. During his career, Miller has served as an adviser, consultant, and visiting professor for many institutions. He has authored or co-authored numerous books, journal articles, and essays, including Emigrants and Exiles: Ireland and the Irish Exodus to North America; Out of Ireland: The Story of Irish Emigration to America; Irish Immigrants in the Land of Canaan: Letters and Memoirs from Colonial and Revolutionary America, 1675-1815; and Ireland and Irish America: Culture, Class, and Transatlantic Migration.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of materials created or collected by Kerby Miller in the course of his research, teaching, and writing on Irish and Irish American history. Materials include photocopies of American Loyalists' petitions to the British government, a run of British Information Services news bulletins concerning conflict in Northern Ireland, and research materials created in the course of his academic scholarship, including original writings, reviews of his work, photocopied letters from Irish immigrants and citizens, and correspondence between Miller and other academics and institutions. Major subjects and themes present in these research files include accounts of Irish family life, pre- and post-immigration economic issues, and experiences coming to and first impressions of living in America.
British Information Services.; American loyalists.; Great Britain |x History |y 20th century.; Ireland |x Emigration and immigration.; Ireland |x History |y 18th century; Northern Ireland |x History |y 1969-1994.; Press and propaganda; United States |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783.; Violence |z Northern Ireland.
- Irish Materials Collected by Miller
  Scope and Content Note
  Materials in this series include a copy of Nicholas Nolan’s 1933 Ph.D. thesis from University College Dublin titled “A Celtic Exodus, or the Irish Emigration”; photocopies of American Loyalists’ petitions during the British government during the American Revolutionary War asking for compensation for losses, explaining their political acts and affiliations, and describing their lives in America; and a run of British Information Services news bulletins on various aspects of the Troubles in Northern Ireland during the late 1980s and early 1990s.
  - American Loyalist Petitions to the British Government, circa 2003 (Box 1)
    Photocopies and related research material of Irish-born American Loyalists' petitions to the British government during the American Revolutionary War. In these letters, the writers ask for compensation for their losses, explaing their political acts and affiliations, and describe their lives in America (including their occupations and emigration history). Other documents include lists and indexes of claimants, as well as the determinations made by the Commission of Inquiry into the Losses and Services of the American Loyalists.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    Photocopies of this material was made from a microfilm collection entitled "American Loyalists: Transcripts of the Manuscript Books and Papers of the Commission of Inquiry into the Losses and Services of the American Loyalists" that was transcribed for the New York Public Library. The original records from which the microfilm collection was created are housed in the Public Record Office of England.
  - British Information Services Bulletins, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
    Collection of weekly or bi-weekly bulletins produced by the British Information Services in New York City concerning the Troubles in the late 1980s and early 1990s. These bulletins acted as propangda policy briefs on various aspects of conflict in Northern Ireland, producing a directed message for media coverage consistent with official British diplomatic policy. Subjects that frequently appear in these bulletins include religion, electoral politics, employment discrimination, paramilitary funerals, law enforcement practices or regulations, and incidents of violence attributed to various Irish republican paramilitary groups, as well as dossiers of republican organizations such as Sinn Fein, the Official Irish Republican Army (IRA), the Provisional Irish Republican Army (IRA or PIRA), and the Irish National Liberation Army (INLA). Also present are excerpts of statements made by officials or other prominent figures.
  - Nolan, Nicholas. "A Celtic Exodus, or the Irish Emigration”, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Academic Research and Writing
  This series consists of Miller's research materials, original writings, and ephemera created in the course of his academic scholarship, including photocopied letters from Irish immigrants and citizens, correspondence between Miller and other academics and institutions, and response to and reviews of Miller's writings. Major subjects and themes present in the research notes and copies of primary source materials include genealogical records, accounts of Irish family life, pre- and post-immigration economic issues, and experiences coming to and first impressions of living in America.
  - Rev. Samuel Blair, 1712-1751 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Memoir (Probably from Journal Notes): Rev. John Craig, 1704-1774 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rev. John Craig, 1740s-1760s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mary Cummings: Research Material, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mary Cummings: Letters, 1811-1815 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Margaret Carey Murphy Burke, undated (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - McAleer Research: Margaret Carey, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Thomas Shipboy, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Shipboy Letters, 1766 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reviews: Field Day Book, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Reviews: Emigrants and Exiles, circa 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Reviews: Irish Immigrants in the Land of Canaan, circa 2003 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Reviews: Miscellaneous Essays, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Reviews: Coffee Table Books, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Reviews: Pop Culture, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Journalism on Kerby Miller, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Films and Film Reviews, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - San Patricios Film, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Bernard M'Kenna Letters, 1811-1812 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Bernard M'Kenna Research Materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 3-4, Box 10, Folder 1)
  - David Lindsey, 1660-1775 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - David Lindsey: Research Material, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Johnstone (From Ireland) Letters, 1773-1808 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Moses Johnston: Reserach Materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Devereux Family Letters, 1798-1800 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - John Devereaux, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - McNish/ Kerr Letters, 1806-1820 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Alexander McNish: Research Materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Anon Ulster Poet (In Irish), 1660-1775 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rev. James McSparron, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Robert Parke, 1725 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Robert Parke, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Chester Co. Quaker Meeting House Photo, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - John Rea: Letter, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - John Rea: Research Materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Dunlop Letters, 1785-1811 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - John Dunlop, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - John Smilie Letter, circa 1762 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - John Smylie, Voyage Letter, circa 1760 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - John O'Row, circa 1809 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - John O'Row: Research Materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - B.8. Thomas Hinds, circa 1795 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Shepherd/ Wanborough, 1700-1741 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Thomas Shepherd, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scottish Tenant's Letter, 1710-1730 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Londonberry, N.H. Petitions, 1720-1730 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Dr. Charles Carrel, 1748 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Charles Lewis Reily Letter, circa 1749 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Samuel Bryan Letter, circa 1752 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Rev. Thomas Barton, circa 1760 - 1770 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Thos. Barton (Finished Materials), undated (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Thomas Burke Letters, 1769-1774 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - Thomas Burke, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Rev. Francis Alison, circa 1760 - 1770 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Rev. Francis Alison: Letters, Philadelphia Rev. Gilbert Tennent (Nov. 1741) PA., 1741-1772 (Box 5, Folder 14 - 15)
  - Morton, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Greer Family Letters, 1764-1808 (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - Thomas Wright, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - James McCullough Research, undated (Box 5, Folder 20, Box 6, Folder 1-2, Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth Brownlee Petition, undated (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Daniel Kent Letters, 1785-1794 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Kent Memoir, undated (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - John and Jane Chambers, 1783-1814 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - John and Jane Chambers Research Materials, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Wright Family Letters, circa 1801-1860 (Box 6, Folder 10, Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Joseph Wright Research Materials, undaetd (Box 10, Folder 6, Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Jame McCullough Journal, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Edward Toner Letters, circa 1815 - 1844 (Box 10, Folder 4, Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Edward and Mary Toner, 1814-1844 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Crockett Family Letters, circa 1796-1851 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Crocket's, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Crocket Letters, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Crockett, James, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Blake Family Letters, 1660-1776 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Maine Scots-Irish Petition, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Robert Witherspoon: Memoir, 1737 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Robert Witherspoon: Research Materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - James Magraw Letters, 1733 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mary Greenlee Deposition, circa 1730 (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  - Matthew Carey Political Letters, circa 1780-1800 (Box 7, Folder 10 - 11)
  - 1799 St. Mary's Church Riot, Philadelphia (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Fr. Patrick Kenny Diary, circa 1790-1820 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - MacArthur Letters, undated (Box 7, Folder 14-15)
  - John Nevin: Letter, 1804 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - John Nevin: Research Materials, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Emmett/ Simms Letter, 1807 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - William Heazelton: Letters, circa 1810-1815 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - William Heazelton: Research Materials, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - John Caldwell: Letter (98 Exile), circa 1783-1814 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - More John Caldwell, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - John Caldwell: Research Materials, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Chester Co. Petitions, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - More Servants and Laborers, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Irish Criminal Memoirs, 1765 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - James Patton Memoi, circa 1783-1814 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Mathew Carey Petitions (Brie), undated (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Brown Family Letters, circa 1793-1816 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Samuel, James, Thomas Brown, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Brown, Revisions, Philadelphia, Strikes, Etc, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Francis Campbell, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Robert Pillson: Letters, circa 1764-1765 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Robert Pillson: Research Materials, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - John (O) Kelly, 1773 (Box 8, Folder 18, Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Redic-Burke (and Findlay, Bryan, Etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 19, Box 10, Folder 2)
  - John Kennedy Petition (from Truxes), circa 1753 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Benj Chandlee Letters, circa 1705 - 1707 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Chester Co., Pennsylvania Servants Petitions, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - John McDonnell, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Morton Background Info, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Caldwell Family Letters, circa 1774 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - James Caldwell: Research Materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Matthew Patton: Diary, circa 1774-1776 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Matthew Patton: Journal, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - South Carolina Loyalists' Petitions, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Loyalists' Petition (Crary Article), undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Job Johns on Letters, circa 1776-1784 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Job Johnston: Research Materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Reddick-Burke Letters, circa 1787-1788 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Post-Revolution Politics, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - John McDonnell, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - McCurtin, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Photocopies from the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)